Guide to the records of the Musical Acoustics Research Library (MARL) M1711
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 3. Arthur H. Benade Collection, 1956-1987; 19.182 Linear Feet; Between 1982 and late 1987: After cancer was diagnosed in the fall of 1982, Benade made increased use of detailed projections (with many pages hand-drawn) for many of his lectures. Though casual in appearance, these were planned
  The major part of Benade's acoustical research effort was spent on the woodwinds and brasses. He supplemented his more formal knowledge with experience gained from playing music on modern and historical instruments (he was an accomplished clarinetist and flute player), and he also used whatever he could find of the vast informal and anecdotal knowledge that has traditionally guided craftsmen and players. His collection of over 130 wind instruments helped him trace design changes in winds from the classical era to the present. As his understanding grew he tested it via the design, construction, and modification of instruments; some that he made or modified have been used by leading players and manufacturers.
  His highly original work led to greater understanding of mode conversion in flared horns, a realistic yet mathematically tractable model of the bore of woodwind instruments based on the acoustics of a lattice of tone holes, development of the concept of cutoff frequencies for isotropic and anisotropic radiation from a woodwind instrument, and clarification of both linear and nonlinear processes in musical instruments and their interrelationships. He explored the dynamics of musical sound radiation, transmission behavior of sound in rooms, and the nature of auditory perception processes associated with hearing in rooms and concert halls. He was the first researcher to attempt to treat the entire tonal production process in wind instruments as a single entity comprised of the influence of the player's windway; the behavior of the instrument's reed, air column, and radiation patterns; the actions of the room on the sound; and the response of the player's aural and neurological sensory equipment.
  Benade's writings include numerous scientific papers and two books: Horns, Strings and Harmony and Fundamentals of Musical Acoustics. Dover Books has issued reprints of both volumes. He wrote two articles for Scientific American magazine and entries for the American Institute of Physics Encyclopedia of Physics, the New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians, and the Academic Press Encyclopedia of Physical Science and Technology.
  Benade received the Acoustical Society of America's Silver Medal (for musical acoustics) and its Gold Medal (for overall excellence in acoustics). He served as the Acoustical Society's Vice President and also chaired its Technical Committee on Musical Acoustics. He was a President of the Catgut Acoustical Society; a member of the Technical Advisory Committee of Pierre Boulez's Institut de Recherche et Coordination Acoustique/Musique in Paris; an advisor to the Dayton C. Miller Collection of Flutes at the Library of Congress; and an Honorary Member of the National Association of Band Instrument Repair Technicians. His many talks before scientific, educational, and musical organizations in the USA and Europe included a series in Stockholm sponsored by the Swedish Royal Academy of Music and the Plenary Session Lecture in Musical Acoustics at the 9th International Congress on Acoustics in Madrid.
  - Acoustical Theory - Woodwind BOIK (Book of Infinite Knowledge) misc. subjects, 1970-1986; cd481fh1920 (Box 74, Folder 1)
  - Acoustical Theory - Scaling Woodwinds to a New Pitch, 1972-1986; bd299jg3112 (Box 74, Folder 2)
    1. On scaling a woodwind to a new pitch [242 KB, DjVu], 5-4-72. 9 pp 2. On scaling a recorder to a new pitch, July 1972. 3 pp 3. On scaling an oboe to a new pitch, August 1977. 4 pp 4. Scaling a reed woodwind to a new pitch, 12-12-77. 6 pp 5. Scaling a woodwind to a new pitch, version 2, 12-12-77. 3 pp 6. To transpose the proportions of a nonmechanized woodwind to a new playing pitch (typed except for a sketch to help define terminology), 6-27-86. 3 pp
  - Acoustical Theory - A pipe with many side holes: calculations, 1955-1958; nn654gk0828 (Box 74, Folder 3)
  - Acoustical Theory - Perturbations of Classical Systems, 1957; wr957jn6234 (Box 74, Folder 4)
  - Acoustical Theory - Mathematical Theory of Woodwind Fingerholes: Notes, Abstract, News release, 1959; wy424zs4439 (Box 74, Folder 5)
  - Acoustical Theory - New Impedance Head, 1972-1973; gc896sp6235 (Box 74, Folder 6)
  - Acoustical Theory - Bore and Tonehole Perturbation Methods, 1969-1980; jb370qc5795 (Box 74, Folder 7)
  - Acoustical Theory - Perturbation Curves for Woodwinds, 1970-1976; nz241bc0618 (Box 74, Folder 8)
  - Acoustical Theory - Perturbation Curves for Brasses, 1977; yq082cm7802 (Box 74, Folder 9)
  - Acoustical Theory - Probe Microphone Design, 1974-1975; zf260gj3858 (Box 74, Folder 10)
  - Acoustical Theory - Brass Instrument Regeneration, 1975; gx303zs5791 (Box 74, Folder 11)
  - Acoustical Theory - Wind Instruments, miscellaneous notes, 1955-1963; zw908sf1820 (Box 74, Folder 12)
  - Acoustical Theory - Sounds with Multiple Parentage, 1973-1975; cd481fh1920 (Box 74, Folder 13)
  - Acoustical Theory - The Tacet Horn: Design and Properties, 1964-1984; fq332hc3250 (Box 75, Folder 1)
  - Acoustical Theory - On Tone Holes, tx157yr6139 (Box 75, Folder 2)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    File missing.
  - Acoustical Theory - Register Holes: Theory and Design, 1958-1980; nw166wy0879 (Box 75, Folder 3)
  - Acoustical Theory - Cutoff Frequencies on Woodwinds, 1972-1981; hm421dw0274 (Box 75, Folder 4)
  - Acoustical Theory - Sound Production in Wind Instruments. Manuscript-in-process, bn536cb1915 (Box 75, Folder 5)
  - Acoustical Theory - Fiddle Spectrum Shifts: Violin Regeneration via Losses from Body Resonances, 1986; gk824vv0248 (Box 75, Folder 6)
  - Acoustical Theory - Spectral Similarities of 'Most Useful' Musical Instrument Sounds, 1980-1981; mm768xw6196 (Box 75, Folder 7)
  - Acoustical Theory - Spectrum Transformation Function, 1971-1975; xj608xd4653 (Box 75, Folder 8)
  - Acoustical Theory - Discrete Spectrum Measurements in Rooms: Calculations, Data, and Manuscript Drafts, 1968-1969; nj991qh5751 (Box 75, Folder 9)
  - Acoustical Theory - Auditory System Coding Seminars, 1985; kh820nz2407 (Box 76, Folder 1)
  - Acoustical Theory - Perception, miscellaneous, 1978; yt322nz5636 (Box 76, Folder 2)
  - Acoustical Theory - Perception Effects for 'Real' Musical Sounds in Rooms, 1981; pz435dh5711 (Box 76, Folder 3)
  - Acoustical Theory - Manuscripts and Calculations for Resonance Absorption Cross-Section Paper, 1963-1965 (Box 76, Folder 4)
  - Acoustical Theory - Manuscripts and Calculations for External Surface Absorption of a Pipe Organ, 1964-1966; dq697bv4305 (Box 76, Folder 5)
  - Acoustical Theory - Photocopy of part of Mahillon's Instruments à vent. (Used for External Surface Absorption paper), sn240rh6124 (Box 76, Folder 6)
  - Acoustical Theory - "Sharpness" of Musical Spectra, 1986 (Box 109, Folder 3)
    Box Numbering
    Gaps in box numbering reflect materials that were incorporated at a later date.
  - Acoustical Theory - "Sharpness" of Musical Spectra. Sharpness Program and Documentation, IML; Terhardt's Pitch Alogorithm Program, IML, 1984 (Box 109, Folder 4)
  - Acoustical Theory - "Sharpness" of Musical Spectra. Research by grad student Ian M. Lindevald under Benade's supervision., 1987 (Box 109, Folder 5)
  - Acoustical Theory - Spiro Kouzoupis, Spectrum Massage. Misc. Programs and Files, 1985 (Box 109, Folder 6)
  - Acoustical Theory - Spectra: German Bassoon, 1980 (Box 109, Folder 7)
  - Acoustical Theory - Spectra: French Bassoon, 1985 (Box 109, Folder 8)
  - Acoustical Theory - Spectra: Flute, 1974-1985 (Box 109, Folder 9)
  - Acoustical Theory - Spectra: NX Clarinet, 1983-1986 (Box 109, Folder 10)
  - Acoustical Theory - Spectra: Chotteau's Clarinet, 1984-1986 (Box 109, Folder 11)
  - Acoustical Theory - Waves in Curved Ducts, 1971-1980 (Box 109, Folder 12)
  - Acoustical Theory - Room Acoustics: Volume Perturbation of Rooms, with Dave Fisch. Term paper for Acoustics 323, 1979 and follow up by Benade 1980; Sound Files in Rooms. Misc. calculations and experiments, 1974; Perceptions in Rooms. Misc. calculations and experiments, 1971; Notes on a Cleveland Orchestra Recording Session, by Douglas Keefe, with Benade's annotations, 1983, 1971 - 1983 (Box 109, Folder 13)
  - Acoustical Theory - Wave Impedance, (handwritten notes), 1974 - 1980 (Box 110, Folder 1)
  - Acoustical Theory - On the Propagation of Sound Waves in a Cylindrical Duct. Research material for a JASA paper, (notes, calculations, and correspondence), 1968 (Box 110, Folder 2)
  - Acoustical Theory - Volume Perturbers as Possible Sound Field Randomizes in Room-Average Spectrum Measurement Procedures. Work by grad student I.M. Lindevald, (notes, calculations, and graphs), 1980 -1982 (Box 110, Folder 3)
  - Acoustical Theory - Notes and Calculations on Ya Gokhishtein's Paper, "Frequency-Coinciding Resonances of Sound Absorption and Amplification in an Expanding Waveguide with a Gas Flow," (reprint and Benade's handwritten notes), 1984 (Box 110, Folder 4)
  - Acoustical Theory - Rubberfilled Capillary Probe Microphone. On Victor Langelo's Project, 1978 - 1979 (Box 110, Folder 5)
  - Acoustical Theory - Nearfield of an Open Pipe End, (handwritten notes and calculations); Pressure Distribution Near a Pipe End, (handwritten notes, calculations, and graphs); Notes in Response to the ASA Minneapolis Meeting, Oct. 1984, (handwritten notes and calculations), 1979 - 1984 (Box 110, Folder 6)
  - Acoustical Theory - Tape Recorder Transposition of Standard Violin. To Simulate the Highest Seven Members of Carleen M. Hutchins' Family of True Violins, (typescript, calculations, and violin sheet music by Jacques Féréol Mazas); Program Plots, (printouts), 1970; This study shows Benade's participation in Hutchin's early violin octet research. (Box 110, Folder 7)
  - Acoustical Theory - On the Effects of Wall Material. Wall Vibration Drive from the Standing Wave, (handwritten notes, calculations and diagrams) and other related material, 1960 - 1984 (Box 110, Folder 8)
  - Acoustical Theory - Temperature Effects in Wind Instrument Air Columns, (typescripts, graphs, reprints), 1945 - 1969 (Box 110, Folder 9)
  - Acoustical Theory - Regeneration in Nonlinear Systems II; Phenomenology of the Regenerative System of Wind Instruments, (typescripts and handwritten notes), 1958 - 1976 (Box 110, Folder 10)
  - Acoustical Theory - Reed Type Regeneration, misc. (handwritten notes, calculations, and diagrams), 1968 - 1973 (Box 110, Folder 11)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Wind Instrument Patents, 1961-1979; rh069pq4485 (Box 76, Folder 7)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Serial Numbers, Dates, Makers, Styles, Miscellany, 1977-1981; xp736jw4722 (Box 76, Folder 8)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Instrument Dimensions, 1948-1950; kf947gv6905 (Box 76, Folder 9)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Blueprints: Bassoon, Oboe, and Clarinet, 1951-1952; rh289qy3210 (Box 76, Folder 10)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Serro Stability of Controlled Stimulus Excitation Systems. High Frequency Audiometer, Calculations, etc. 1979, (letters, notes, calculations and graphs); Design Notes for a Repetition-Rate Extractor, 1983, (notes, figures, and calculations); High Frequency Plotter Graphics, 1985, (annotated printouts, figures, and calculations); Dual Tone-Source Circuits, 1985, (figures and calculations), 1979 - 1985 (Box 76, Folder 11)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Misc. Fingering Charts (Box 77, Folder 1)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Reprints on Historical Instruments and Acoustics (Box 77, Folder 2)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - General Music Reprints, 1950-1962 (Box 77, Folder 3)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Unsorted References and Reprints I, 1938-1972 (Box 77, Folder 4)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Unsorted References and Reprints II, 1946-1982 (Box 77, Folder 5)
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Traces of Reverberation Time Measurements of Blossom Music Center. Performed by A. Benade and possibly R. Shakland, (machine generated printouts, identified, with partial certitude, by Peter Hoekje), 1969 (Box 60, Folder 6)
    Gap in box numbering is due to oversize materials.
  - Aids to Acoustical Research - Notebook I, Nov. 1964-Dec. 1967; Notebook II, Oct. 1976 - May 1977, 1964-1976 (Box 112, Folder 8)
  - Testing Research Equipment - Impedance Head I: Pedersen Transient Chart Recorder 57-TR. Chart recorder strips, 1982-86 (data, calculations, diagrams, and correspondence); Probe Mikes (Dynamic), 1979-80, (data, calculations, and diagrams); Frequency Response of a Transducer Disk Driving a Cavity on the End of a Long Cylinder, 1985, (notes, diagrams, calculations); Strobocom Model 6T-2. Benade bought this in 1980, (manual, etc.); Resonator Drawings by Murday, 1966-1967, drawings, calculations, and notes); Merhaut Type Impedance Head, 1968-69, (drawings, calculations, and notes); Admittance Head. Make 1, Brass, 1979, (diagram, notes, and calculations); Piezo-Disk Transducers. Mouth/Mouthpiece, 1983-84, (diagram, notes, and calculations); Impedance Head, Mag/Electret, Merhaut, 1980, (diagrams, graphs, and notes); Experiments with Electret Mikes. Layouts, CKTS, Calibration, Benade and Doug Keefe, 1976-86, (diagrams, graphs, and notes), 1966-1986 (Box 118, Folder 1)
  - Testing Research Equipment - Impedance Head II: Coaxial Pz/Electret Impedance Head, 1986, (diagrams and notes); Piezo Driver. Sine/Impulse conditioner, 1982, (diagrams, calculations, and notes); Oboe Impedance Head with Piezo Driver Electret Mike, 1985, (diagrams, and notes); Piezo Disc/ Electret Tranducer for Clarinet, 1984, (diagrams, calculations, tables, and notes); Heterodyne-Type Transcient Extractor, Benade, Tom Finsch, Spiro Kouzoupis, and Steven Lutgen, 1972-1988, (diagrams, calculations, tables, notes, and slides of power boards); X 10 Piezo-Driver Voltage Amplifier, 1983, (diagrams, calculations, tables, and notes); Properties of the Piezoelectric Disc Feedback Transduces, 1979, (diagrams, calculations, and notes) (Box 118, Folder 2)
  - Testing Research Equipment – Douglas H. Keefe Probe Mike Filter, 1979-80, (tables, diagrams, graphs, and notes); Directional Coupler, 1967-81, (tables, diagrams, graphs, notes, calculations, and sheet music); Driver Isolation Tank, 1980, (diagrams, notes, and graphs); Clarinet-Blowing Machine, Fortram Computer Program, 1967-69, (computer printout, tables, diagrams, and notes); Drawings for Driver Hardware, 1964, (drawings); Filter Boxes, 1968-69, (diagrams and notes); Frequency Response Filters, 1981-82, (graphs, calculations, tables, and notes); Sin-Cos Osc and Multiplier, for a Benade, Worman paper, 1968, (diagrams and notes); Rotating Head Tape Deck, 1973, (diagrams and notes), 1964-1982 (Box 118, Folder 3)
  - Testing Research Equipment – Portable Oscillator and Det[ector?], 1968, (diagrams and graphs); Consolidated Controls Corp. Differential Pressure Transducer 0-3 PSID, 1981, (diagram and notes); Condenser Mike Power Supplies, 1963, (diagram, notes, and calculations); Electric Organ Layout, 19890, (diagram, notes, tables, and calculations); Trumpet Driver and Mike, 1965-71, (sound spectra); Chirp Trigger Box, 1984, (diagrams and notes); 1-20 Hz Servo for Reed Experiment Air Supply, 1984, (graphs, calculations, and notes); Adjustable Reed Holder, 1982, (diagrams, tables, and notes); Spark Impulse Source Model 3, with Jack Smith, 1981-84, (diagrams and notes); Flutter and Wow Piezo Device, 1979, (diagrams and calculations); Magnetic Drive Small Impedance Head, 1st Version, 1970, (calculations, notes and graphs), 1963-1984 (Box 118, Folder 4)
  - Testing Research Equipment – Vibration Pickup, (diagrams and calculations); Misc. Circuits and Changes to Equipment, 1963-67, (diagrams, notes, calculations, and tables); Servo Regulator IV, with DBX and AD 521, 1981, (diagrams and tables); Dual-Step Attenuator Box, 1970-80, (diagrams and notes); Signal-Controlled Attennator No.2, Benade’s first transistorized version, 1963, (diagrams, notes, and calculations); Servo Regulator III C.O.L., 1979, (diagrams); Diode-Type Signal Compressor, 1980, (graphs, diagrams, and calculations); Tuned Amplifier. Multi-loop Active Filter, 1974, (calculations, notes, and sound spectra); Preamplifier for Unigon Analyzer, 1980, (diagram and notes); General Purpose Amplifier, R. A. Leskovec, 1981, (diagrams and notes), 1963-1981 (Box 118, Folder 5)
  - Testing Research Equipment – Mike Calibration Curves, 1966-78, (graphs, sound spectra, calculations, notes, and correspondence); Zero-Crossing Gate, with Kurt Larson, 1979, (diagrams and slides); Log Amplifier for Reverberation Time Measurements, 1977, (diagram, graph, and photos); PZT Mikes. Gift from John Serafini, 1964-81, (letter, diagrams, notes); Portable Lab Setup, 1975-78 Version, with Bob Miller, (typescript, diagrams, notes, calculations, and reprint); Wavetek Mod. 185 VCO, 1980, (graph and table); G. R. Tuned Amplifier. Type 1232-A. General Radio Company, with Gary Chanan, 1968, (graphs and tables), 1964-1981 (Box 119, Folder 1)
  - Wind Instruments - Physics of Tone Color in Wind Instruments. Lecture at Akron Physics Club, 1969, (lecture notes and figures, 4 pp.); What Makes a Wind Instrument Good? Lecture at Miami University, 1970, (lecture notes, 4 pp.); The Tone of Wind Instruments: Science and Art Entwined. Lecture at Grand Valley College, Allendale, MI, 1970, (lecture notes, 2 pp.); Acoustics of Wind Instrument Tone Color and Response. Lecture at University of KY, 1971, (lecture notes, 3 pp.); Toward Good Tone and Response in Wind Instruments. Lecture at Kent State University, 1971, (lecture notes, 2 pp.); Response and Tone of Wind Instruments. Lecture at CWRU Colloquium, 1971, (lecture notes and figures, 13 pp.); What Makes a Wind Instrument Good? Lecture at Thiel College, Greenville, PA, (lecture notes and figures, 4 pp.); Toward Really Good Wind Instruments. Lecture at Edimboro State College, 1971, (lecture notes and figures, 18 pp.); Physics of Wind Instruments: Tone and Response. Talk at the AAAS General Science Symposium on Sound and Music, organized by Carleen M. Hutchins and Arthur H. Benade, 1971, (announcement and annotated typescript with figures for talk 18 pp.), 1969 - 1971 (Box 112, Folder 6)
    Gap in box numbering due to materials added to the collection at a later date.
  - Wind Instruments - The Pursuit of Wind Instruments. Lecture for Platteville, WI, 1972, (notes for lecture 7 pp.); Elementary Sketch of the Workings of Quantum Mechanics; What is a Really Good Wind Instrument? Lectures for Dickenson College, Carlisle, PA, 1972, (lecture notes 4 pp.); New Woodwind Screeches and Baroque Oboes; Woodwind Cousins of Solid -State Physics. Lectures for Miami University, OH, 1972, (lecture notes 9 pp.); The Physics of Really Good Wind Instruments. Lecture for the University of Wisconsin Physics Colloquium, 1972, (lecture notes 7 pp.); Woodwinds as Irregular Lattice Structures. Lecture for CWRU Colloquium, 1972, (lecture notes and figures 14 pp.); The Pursuit of Wind Instruments. Lecture for the Carnegie-Mellon Physics Colloquium, 1972, (lecture notes 4 pp.); Woodwinds as Nonlinear Oscillators. Lecture for Rutgers Colloquium, 1973, (lecture notes 7 pp.); The Pursuit of Good Woodwinds. Lecture for Arizona State University, 1973, (lecture notes 3 pp.); Woodwinds as Nonlinear Oscillators. Lecture for Kent State Colloquium, 1973, (lecture notes 5 pp.); The Cause and Cure of Woodwinds. Lecture for the Illionois Institute of Technology, 1973, (lecture notes 4 pp.); Cause and Cure of Woodwinds. Lecture at Bell Labs., Holmdel, NJ, 1973, (lecture notes 5 pp.); In Pursuit of Woodwinds. Graduate Lecture Program Convocation. N. Illinois Univ. DeKalb, 1973, (lecture notes 3 pp.); The Clarinet as a Pseudo-Random Lattice. Technical Talk. N. Illinois Univ. DeKalb, 1973, (lecture notes 2 pp.), 1972 - 1973 (Box 112, Folder 7)
  - Wind Instruments - The Interplay of Technology and Music in Wind Instruments Since the Baroque Era. Lecture for Bowling Green State University, OH, (lecture notes, 3 pp.); In Pursuit of Woodwinds. Lecture for Lebanon Valley College, Annual Band Clinic, Annville, PA, (lecture notes, 2 pp. and correspondence); Strange Sounds from Woodwinds. (Demonstration lecture on production and perception of multiphonics) for CWRU, (lecture notes and slides, 12 pp.); What Makes a Woodwind Instrument Good? Lecture for the Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, ILL, (lecture notes 3 pp. and letter); The Physics of Woodwinds. Lecture for Princeton University, (lecture notes 6 pp.); Wind Instruments Lecture Series for University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, (class notes and handouts); Influences of Wall Material in the Construction and Playing of Musical Wind Instruments. Lecture Physics Soc. Buffalo, NY, (announcement, notes and slide); The Physics of Woodwind Instruments. Tone Color and Response. Lecture for the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, (notes for lecture, 5 pp.); Talk to Music Schools and Bands Around the State. Lecture Michigan State University, (lecture notes, 3pp.), 1974 (Box 113, Folder 1)
  - Wind Instruments - New Research: Can One Devise Yet Another Woodwind? For the CWRU Lecture Series "Physics Today," 1975, (announcement, preliminary calculations, notes, and figures); What Makes a Wind Instrument Good? Lecture for Morrisville State College, NY, 1975, (lecture notes and correspondence); What Makes a Wind Instrument Good? Lecture for North Carolina State University, Raleigh, N.C., 1975, (lecture notes and correspondence); Adjustment of Woodwinds as a Problem in Perturbation Theory. Lecture for Ohio Section APS, Ball State University, Muncie IN, 1975, (lecture notes and figures 5 pp.); What is an Excellent Woodwind? University of Iowa, Sigma Xi Lecture, 1975, (lecture notes 5 pp.); The Physics of Woodwind Tone and Response. Lecture for the University of Iowa Physics Colloquium, 1975, (lecture notes and correspondence 9 pp.); The Pursuit of Woodwinds. Lecture for the University of Delaware, DE, 1975, (lecture notes 2 pp.); The Perfect Wind Instrument; From Player to Listener Via Instrument and Room. Lectures for the Acoustical Society of America, Austin Regional Chapter, 1978, (announcement, letters, lecture notes, and 2 figures by either David Braslau or A. W. Nolle); Wind Instrument Radiation Systematics. Lecture for Pennsylvania State University, PA, 1981, (lecture notes and one slide 5 pp.);Effect of Wall Material on Wind Instrument Sound Production. Argonne National Laboratory, Physics Division, Colloquium Talk, 1981, (lecture notes and figures, 10 pp.); Woodwinds: The Technical-Musical Path Since 1700. Pre-concert Lecture for the Cleveland Orchestra, 1983, (lecture notes, musical examples, and lecture program, 8 pp.); Evolution of Woodwinds as a Problem in Physics. Colloquium lecture for Boston University MA, Physics Department, 1985, (slides of lecture notes, figures, and musical examples 16 pp.); What is a Woodwind? Lecture for the American Vacuum Society, 1986, (slides of lecture notes and figures 4 pp.), 1975 - 1986 (Box 113, Folder 2)